所有战犯排队进入
The war criminals will proceed in orderly fashion...
候车室并等候指示
to the main waiting room and await instructions.
不许讲话！ 服从守卫！
No talking. obey the guards
战犯必须到候车室！
War criminals must proceed to the main waiting room.
讲话者将被严惩！
Those caught talking will be severely punished
皇上！
The emperor.
皇上
Your Majesty.
他们以为他们在干吗？
What do they think they are doing?
站住！危险！
Get up. It is dangerous
回去 快回去！
Go back. Go back. Go!
你们疯了？！ 他们会把我们都杀了！
Are you mad? They could kill us all.
去！去！
Go. Go
开门！
open the door!
妈妈！
Mama.
钦承慈禧端佑
By the command of Her Imperial Majesty...
康颐昭豫庄诚
also called the Compassionate and the Blessed..
寿恭钦献崇熙
the Respectful and the Long-living..
皇太后懿旨
the Empress Dowager commands..
爱新觉罗溥仪
Aisin-Gioro Pu Yi..
醇亲王的儿子
son of Prince Chun...
着即刻送往
shall be transferred immediately..
紫禁城
to the Forbidden City..
并且留在那里
and will remain in the Great Within..
等候圣谕
awaiting Her Majesty's decision
钦此！
Respect this!
阿嬷 我把我儿子给你
Ar Mo, I am giving you my son.
- 我的儿子就是你的儿子！-快！快！
- My son is your son. - Quick! Quick!
我要回家！
I want to go home.
不行 看看紫禁城
No. Look at the Forbidden City
把他给我
Give him to me.
嬷嬷！
Ar Mo!
溥仪 到这儿来
Pu Yi, come here.
你这么小
How small you are.
你怕我吗？
Are you afraid of me?
每个人都怕
Everyone is.
我是至高无尚的慈禧太后
I am the Grand Empress Dowager.
我在这里住了好久好久了
And I have lived here for a long, long time.
他们叫我老佛爷
And they call me the old Buddha
这是牡丹
This is Peony.
喜欢她吗？
Do you like her?
你知道
Men, you know..
天黑后男人就 不允许留在紫禁城了
are not allowed in the Forbidden City after dark.
甚至象你这样的小孩！
Even little men like you
唯一能住在这里的男人
The only man who can live here..
是皇上
is the emperor.
但是皇帝现在在天堂
But the emperor is on high...
驭龙而去！
riding the dragon now
他今天驾崩了!
He died today.
万岁
Longevity.
这些其他的男人 并不是真正的男人
These other men...They are not real men.
他们都是太监
They are all eunuchs.
现在 他们都在等着我死
And now they are all waiting for me to die.
所以
That is why...
他们把我的床放在房子中间
they are putting my bed in the middle ofthe room...
上面吊了黑珍珠
under the black pearl.
小溥仪
Little Pu Yi..
我决定
I have decided...
封你为新的万年皇帝
that you will be the new Lord of 10,000 Years.
你将成为天子
You will be the Son of Heaven.
我们回家吗 爸爸？
Are we going home, Papa?
嘘！嘘！
Shh! Shh!
嘘！ 就快完了
Shh. It will soon be over.
看！
Look!
Look.
蟋蟀！
Cricket!
蟋蟀！蟋蟀！蟋蟀在哪儿？
Cricket! Cricket! where's the cricket?
它是奴才的朋友 皇上
Ah, he is my friend, Your Majesty.
在奴才臂下安全又暖和
Safe and warm under my arm.
陪奴才长途旅行到这里
Kept me company on the longjourney here.
看？
Ah. See?
他在给皇上叩头
He is kowtowing to Your Majesty.
现在 他是皇上的蟋蟀了！
Now he can be the emperor's cricket.
皇上 这就是紫禁城
Your Majesty, this is the Forbidden City
看
Look.
这一小块是皇上的寝宫
- This little one is Your Majesty's bedroom. -
- 这是奴才们的 - 今天我回家吗？
- This is where we are. - Am I going home today?
不是今天
Not today.
不行的
Not yet.
还有这里 看 这儿是太和殿
And here. Look. This is the Hall of Supreme Harmony...
皇帝在这儿登基
where Your Majesty was crowned.
皇上 这是万寿门
I give Your Majesty the Gate of Marshovala
这是万寿门
I give you the Marshio Gate.
- 门  - 是的 是的
- The gate. - Yes. Yes.
还有大成殿
And the Palace of the Cloudless Heaven
是的
And - Yes.
皇上 您的御浴准备好了！
Your Majesty, your imperial bath is ready.
我不喜欢洗澡！
I don't like baths!
我不喜欢洗澡！我不喜欢洗澡！
I don't like baths I don't like baths
今天没有燕窝
No bean curd today...
也没肉！
and no meat!
真的我想干什么就可以干什么？
Is it true I can do anything I want?
当然 皇上
Of course, Your Majesty.
干什么都行
Anything you want.
您是万岁爷啊
You are the Lord of 1 0,000 Years.
噢！噢！噢！ 不！别泼我脸！
oh! Oh, no! Not in my face.
我是天子！ 我是天子！
I'm the Son of Heaven! I'm the Son of Heaven!
是！是的！
Oh, yes! oh, yes!
我是天子！
I am the Son of Heaven!
阿嬷 我想要回家
Ar Mo. I want to go home.
我想要回家 我想要回家
I want to go home. I want to go home.
我想要回家 阿嬷 我想要回家
I want to go home, Ar Mo. I want to go home.
从前啊…
Once upon a time...
有一颗大树
there was a great tree...
和一阵大风
and a great wind.
当大树倒下…
And when the tree fell...
猴子都跑散了…
- the monkeys were scattered
他的汤都冷了
- His soup is getting cold.
- 我在哪里？ - 在中华人民共和国
- where am I? - In the People's Republic of China.
- 为什么拦住我？ - 你是战犯 你必须受到审判
- Why did you stop me? - You are a criminal. You must bejudged.
我重复一遍
I repeat!
战俘回房间时要低着头
Prisoners going to their cells will walk with their heads bowed.
眼睛看着地！
Keep your eyes on the ground.
不许四处张望！
- No looking forward or to the side.
守卫将带着你们 告诉你们何时转弯！
The guards will give you directions and tell you when to turn.
溥杰
Pu Chieh.
您的客人在等着见您  皇上
Your guest is waiting to meet you, Your Majesty.
您的母亲也来了
Also, your mother has arrived.
您已经好多年没见您的母亲了 皇上
You have not seen your mother for manyyears, Your Majesty.
- 他真小！ - 他年青 皇上
- He is so small. - He is young, Your Majesty.
去
Go.
皇帝的弟弟  溥杰阁下
The emperor's brother, His Excellency Pu Chieh.
阿嬷
Ar Mo.
皇上母亲的身体怎样了？
How is the health of His Majesty's mother?
好多了 谢谢您
It is better. Thank you.
皇上长大了！
How much His Majesty has grown.
母亲已经七年没见到朕了！
My mother has not seen me for seven years.
您还能认出朕吗？
Do you remember my face?
不能
No.
那晚他们骑马来的时候 我就料到有这结果
The night they came with the horses, I knew it would be like this.
- 朕的弟弟倒每天能见你！ - 溥杰非常渴望来见您
- My brother sees you every day. - Pu Chieh is very excited to meet you.
他常常谈起您
He often talks about you.
我们都以您为荣
We are all very proud of you.
风筝
The kite.
他给你选的
He chose this for  you.
阿爸！
Papa!
他们把脸扭开了！
They're turning away.
当然！一般人不许直视皇帝！
Of course. ordinary people are not allowed to look at the emperor.
- 朕太重要了 - 想做什么就做什么是真的吗？
- I'm too important. - Is it true that you can do whatever you want?
当然可以 如果朕淘气 就有人代朕受过
Of course I can. If I am naughty, someone else is punished.
他们之一
One of them.
停下！
Stop!
朕要走路
The emperor will walk.
朕没遇到过其他小孩
I have never met other children.
- 他们都跟你一样吗？ - 臣弟有三个姐妹和两个朋友
- Are they all like you? - I've got three sisters and two friends.
如果你来我们家 可以和我们一起玩
If you come to our house, you can play with us.
皇帝从不离开皇宫
The emperor never leaves the palace.
我们一起玩游戏！
We play games together!
朕也知道一个游戏！
I know a game too.
跑！
Run!
船上的都是先王妃
The ones on the boat are the high consorts.
先王妃？ 先皇的妃子
- High consorts? - The wives ofthe emperor before me.
他们说是我的阿妈 但她们不是！她们不是！
They say they're my mother, but they're not. They're not!
为什么你穿那呀？ 你是不能穿黄色的！
Why are you wearing that? You are not allowed to wear yellow.
但这是普通黄色
But this is ordinary yellow.
那是御黄色！
It is imperial yellow.
不 不是！
No, it is not.
我们说它是！只有皇帝可用御黄色！
We say it is. Only the emperor can wear that yellow.
脱了它！ 不！
- Take it off. - No!
脱了它！不！并且你也不再是皇帝了！
- Take it off! - No! And you're not the emperor anymore.
现在有一个新皇帝！
There is a new emperor now
他剪了辨子 不光有骆驼  他还有车！
He has cut off his queue. And instead ofa camel, he has got a car.
你说什么？
What did you say?
你不是皇帝！
You're not the emperor.
撒谎！
Liar!
你再也不是皇帝了！ 撒谎！
- You're not the emperor anymore! - Liar!
撒谎！你不是…
- Liar! - You're not the...
撒谎！
Liar!
你不是皇帝！
You're not the emperor.
撒谎！ 你不是皇帝！
- Liar! - You're not the emperor!
好大胆你！
How dare you!
你不是皇帝！
- You're not the emperor!
别！
Please. No!
皇上！冷静！
Your Majesty. Calm yourself.
你不是皇帝！ 好大胆你！
- You're not the emperor! - How dare you!
皇上！冷静！
oh, Your Majesty. Calm yourself.
我是皇帝不是？
Am I the emperor or not?
皇上永远是皇帝
Your Majesty will always be the emperor.
听到了？ 证明给我看!
- You see? - Prove it.
大脚
Big Foot.
喝了它！
Drink it.
快 喝了墨水
Go on. Drink the green ink.
我让你看看！
I will show you!
看见了？那是他的车！ 他是民国的总统
See? That is a car. He's the president of the Republic.
为什么在这儿垒墙 大臣？
Why is this wall here, Lord Chamberlain?
只是一堵墙 皇上 什么都没变
It is just a wall, Your Majesty. Nothing has changed.
你在说谎
You are lying.
太傅 我还是皇帝吗？
High Tutor, am I still the emperor?
在紫禁城内您永远是皇帝
You will always be the emperor inside the Forbidden City...
但在外面不是
but not outside.
我不明白
I do not understand.
外面是个民国
Outside China is now a republic...
还有个总统
with a president.
嬷嬷在哪儿？
Where is Ar Mo?
嬷嬷？
Ar Mo.
你们都是骗子！
You are all liars!
让我跟他道别！ 快！快！
- Let me say good-bye! - Hurry. Hurry.
他是我的孩子！
He's my child!
阿嬷？
Ar Mo?
我不明白
I do not understand.
皇上现在是个大孩子了 不该再有奶妈了
Your Majesty is a big boy now. He cannot have a wet nurse anymore
这样好多了
It is much better like this.
健康多了
Much healthier.
但她不是我的奶妈
But she is not my wet nurse.
她是我的蝴蝶
She is my buttefrly.
阿嬷！
Ar Mo!
这是感化中心
This is the detention center...
位于公共安全抚顺局
of the Fushun Bureau of Public Security.
我是这里的主管！
And I am the governor.
战争期间  这里是日本的监狱
During the war, this was aJapanese prison
你们大部分可能还记得
Many ofyou may remember it..
因为你们为日本人工作
because you worked with the Japanese
你们要为它的建成负责
You were responsible for building it..
你们还关满了无辜的人
and you filled it with innocent people
怎么会这样呢？
How could this happen?
为什么你们背叛自己的国家？！
Why did you betray your country?
为什么你们会变成战犯呢？
What turned you into war criminals?
我们相信人生来本性是好的
We believe that men are born good.
我们相信改变的唯一方法就是 找出真相 直接面对它
We believe that the only way to change is to discover the truth and look at it in the face.
这就是你们在这里的原因
That is why you are here
你们先要交待清楚生平情况
You will begin by writing the story of your lives...
并坦承罪行
and by confessing your crimes
能否赎罪取决于你们所抱的态度
Your salvation will lie entirely in the attitude you take.
我提议你们要坦诚真挚
I advise you to be frank and sincere
不然，你们不会好过
otherwise, things can still go very badly for you.
几年后…
After a few years...
民国和清末同样腐败
the Chinese Republic had become as corrupt as the old empire.
很快便由军阀及官僚把持
It fell quickly into the hands of ambitious generals and corrupt bureaucrats.
军阀割据时代开始
The era of the warlords had begun
l9l9年5月我获任命时 中国正动荡不安
By May 1919, when I received my appointment, China was in turmoil
皇上，师傅勤见
May the new tutor present himself.
皇上 新师傅来了
Your Imperial Highness, the new tutor.
雷金纳德・费兰芒・庄士敦先生
Mr. Reginald Fleming Johnston
你好 庄士敦先生
How do you do, Mr.Johnston?
你好 皇上
How do you do, Your Majesty?
我们上课吧
Now we will go to school.
皇上 在我的国家  一般要
Your Majesty, in my country, it would be usual to begin...
先考试一下
with some kind ofan examination.
皇帝不能被考
The emperor cannot be examined.
好吧 那只好改一下
Well, that may have to change.
可是 皇上或许想问我一些问题
But first Your Majesty might like to ask me some questions.
你的祖先在哪儿？
Where are your ancestors buried?
苏格兰 皇上
In Scotland, Your Majesty.
那么 你不穿裙子？
But then, where's your skirt?
在你们国家 男人穿短裙子 不是吗？
In your country, men wear short skirts, do they not?
不是 皇上 苏格兰人不穿裙子 他们穿方格呢短裙
No, Your Majesty. Scotsmen do not wear skirts. They wear kilts.
方格呢短裙？ 方格呢短裙
- Kilts? - Kilts.
或许只是一个措词的问题  但是措词非常重要
A matter of words, perhaps, but words are important.
为什么措词重要？
Why are words important?
如果你不能说出你的本意 皇上 那你就不会说话算数了
If you cannot say what you mean, Your Majesty, you will never mean what you say...
一个绅士应该永远说话算数
and a gentleman should always mean what he says.
是的！“绅士”
Ah, yes. A gentleman.
你是绅士吗？
Are you a gentleman?
我非常想做绅士 皇上
I would like to be a gentleman, Your Majesty.
- 我努力去做 - 朕不是绅士
- I try to be. - I am not a gentleman.
朕被禁止说心里话
I'm not allowed to say what I mean.
他们常告诉朕该说些什么
They are always telling me what to say.
皇上尚年轻
Your Majesty is still very young.
皇上也许想看看英、美杂志
I thought he might like to see some English and American magazines.
是我刚收到的
I have just received them.
我知道你所知道的
I know that you know that I know..
我知道的你所知的
that you know that that is a dialogue...
那是孔子和庄子之间的对话
between Confucius and Chuang-Tsu.
注意尊严 皇上
Concerning respect, Your Majesty.
谁是“乔治.华盛顿”？
Who is this George washington?
一个著名的美国人 皇上
A famous American, Your Majesty.
一个革命的将军 美国第一任总统
A Revolutionary general. The first American president.
噢！象苏联的列宁先生？
Ah. Like Mr. Lenin in Russia?
不太一样
Not quite.
他有车吗？
Does he have a car?
他去世很久了 皇上
He lived a long time ago, Your Majesty.
我想要辆车
I want a car.
我认为你的老鼠想逃掉 皇上
I think your mouse is trying to escape Your Majesty.
别把老鼠这秘密告诉别人
Please do not tell anyone about my mouse.
下课了
The lesson is finished.
尝膳的太监是个勇敢的人
The official taster's a brave man
先帝有不少是被毒害的
Many of my ancestors have been poisoned, you know.
皇上每天如此进午膳的吗?
Does Your Majesty have lunch like this every day?
对 每天如是 像做马戏似的
Ah, yes. Every day. Like theater.
朕不知何原因，一向如是
I do not know why. It has always been like that
在西方是如何杀害帝王的?
How do they kill emperors in the West?
奥国皇帝给枪杀，是吗?
The Austrian emperor was shot was he not?
不是 不过他的侄儿大战前给暗杀
No. But his nephew was assassinated before the Great War.
但俄国沙皇就给枪杀了
But the Russian emperor has been shot. He was called a czar.
是的
Yes.
他侵占满州不少地方
He took lots ofour land in Manchuria.
朕是满州人 甚至民国以后，满州仍是朕的国土
I'm a Manchurian. Even after the Republic, it's still my country.
那…秘密 皇上 又出来了
The... secret, Your Majesty, is emerging again.
有什么事吗 皇上？
Is something the matter, Your Majesty?
有事发生
-  Something is happening
发生了什么事 庄士敦先生？
What is happening, Mr.Johnston?
- 没… - 住嘴!
- Nothing is... - Quiet.
前来皇宫时 我们遭一群大学生所阻
on ourway here, Your Majesty, we were held up by students from the university.
他们抗议民国政府
They were protesting against the Republican government...
把国土割让给日本
because it has agreed to give away Chinese territory to Japan.
庄士顿先生…
Is it true, Mr.Johnston...
外面有许多人给砍头 这是真的么？
that many people out there have had their heads chopped off?
是真的，皇上
It is true, Your Majesty.
有许多人被砍头了
Many heads have been chopped off.
使他们不再思考
It does stop them thinking.
皇上该寝息了
It's time for the emperor's rest.
学生愤怒是对的
The students are right to be angry.
朕也愤怒!
I'm angry.
但朕不获准离开紫禁城
But I'm not allowed to leave the Forbidden City.
朕想到外面去
I want to go out, Mr.Johnston.
陛下!
My lord.
朕想看看繁闹城市!
I want to see the city of sounds.
皇上赐你头品顶戴
The emperor awards you with the order of the Ruby Hat Button..
赏坐四人肩舆
and with the right to be carried in your own chair with four bearers.
此人走中道而我走侧道？
Ye'll take the high road and I'll take the low road?
我希望皇上没有忘记
I hope the emperor has not forgotten...
今天的数学课
that this is the day for his maths class.
给皇上的！
For Your Majesty.
太医说脚踏车不好
My doctor said bicycles are bad for you.
对你有害？ 胡说！
Bad for you? Nonsense!
怎么骑？
How does it work?
噢
oh.
很简单
It's simple.
抬起头眼朝前看！
Head up and eyes forward.
就象数学！
As in math.
皇母死了 是吗? 是的 皇上
- My mother's dead, is she not? - Yes, Your Majesty.
微臣替皇上难过
I'm profoundly sorry.
朕不难过
I am not.
她是自杀的 吞下鸦片球
She killed herself. She swallowed a ball of opium.
朕去见她及皇弟
I'm going to see her and my brother.
开门!
Open the door.
open the door!
开门!
Open the door.
麻烦来了！
Trouble maker!
魔头！管闲事的！
Devil! Meddler!
麻烦 除了麻烦就是麻烦
Trouble. Nothing but trouble
看你把我弄成何样子 你是个残忍无知的老头子
- Look where you lead him. - And you are an old, cruel, ignorant man!
这孩子的母亲死了
The boy's mother is dead...
竟不让他去看看！
and he's not even allowed to see her!
朕要出去!
I want to go out!
别动！ 呆在那里别动！
Stop that! Stay where you are!
- 朕要出去! - 别动！
- I want to go out! - Stop it!
- 朕要出去! - 别动！呆在那里别动！笨蛋！
- I want to go out! - Stay where you are! You fool!
别动！
Stay there!
上！
Chang.
驼背 大脚！
Hunchback. Big Foot.
先生
Sir.
把手伸给我 先生
Give me your hand, sir.
你看不到吗？
Can you not see?
请看我的左耳 先生
Look at my left ear, please, sir.
谢谢 再看右耳
Thank you. And now my right.
谢谢
Thank you
请看着我的手指 先生
Would you follow my finger, please, sir?
嗯嗯
Mm-hmm.
非常简单 庄士敦 皇上需要眼镜
Well, it's perfectly simple, Johnston. The emperor needs spectacles.
像莱特一样
Like Harold Lloyd.
不可能
Impossible.
皇上怎能戴眼镜
An emperor does not wear spectacles.
这是不允许的!
That cannot be allowed
时代不同了 殿下！
Times have changed, Your Highnesses.
如果皇上不戴眼镜 庄士敦  他会失明的
If His Majesty doesn't get spectacles, Johnston, he could lose his sight.
皇上
Your Majesty.
如果皇上不戴眼镜  我就辞职
If the emperor does not get spectacles, I will resign.
很不幸 决定不能改
Unfortunately, our decision is final.
很不幸 我要说的将发表在中国的所有报纸上
And unfortunately, what I have to say will be published in every newspaper in China.
您要说什么 庄士敦先生？
What do you have to say, Mr.Johnston?
皇上在宫中有如囚犯 自登基直至逊位
The emperor has been a prisoner in his own palace since the day that he was crowned...
皇上仍是个囚犯
and has remained a prisoner since he abdicated.
皇上长大了会猜想何故
But now he's growing up, he may wonderwhy...
自己是唯一不准出门的人
he is the only person in China who may not walk out of his own front door.
我想皇上是世上最寂寞的孩子
I think the emperor is the loneliest boy on earth.
同样悲惨是…
It would be conveniently sad..
皇上失去视力
if he becomes blind
失去视力…庄士敦先生?
Blind, Mr.Johnston?
其代价 阁下
To the expense, Your Excellency.
要养活一千二百名太监
To the cost of maintaining 1,200 eunuchs...
三百五十名妃嫔以及一百八十五名御厨
350 ladies-in-waiting and 1 85 cooks.
每月买过百貂皮裘 每星期买三干只鸡
To buying 120 sable furs a month and 3,000 chickens a week.
八百四十名待卫及内务府官员
To the fact that 840 guards and employees of the household department...
及一名主管  他们只关心一件事……
plus one lord chamberlain care only about one thing:
中饱私囊
filling their own rice bowls.
你对数字很有一手 庄士顿先生
You are very good at accounts, Mr.Johnston.
皇上也许逊了位
The emperor may have abdicated...
但他对许多人来说仍然是一个重要的象征
but he's still a symbol of great importance to many people.
我亦因有此想法才留下来
If I did not agree with that, I would not be here.
我们当中有人相信有一天
And some of us believe...
皇上不单会是个象征
that one day soon he may be more than a symbol.
眼镜是细节而矣
The spectacles are a detail.
你其实想怎样? 庄士顿先生
What do you really want, Mr.Johnston?
只要眼镜
Just the spectacles.
哦
oh.
婉容 皇上
The princess WanJung Your Majesty.
十七岁
Seventeen years old.
惠珍 十五岁
Princess WhoJen. Fifteen years old.
莉莲 皇上
The princess Li Li, Your Majesty.
还有风英
And the Princess Fun Ying.
她是谁?
who is this?
文秀 十二岁
Princess Wen Hsiu. Twelve years old.
她的脸孔很有趣
She has got a funny face.
不能选一妻子 要一名皇后 一名妃子
Not just one wife. One empress and one secondary consort.
两个妻子？ 但你选谁当皇后？
- Two wives? - But who did you choose to be the empress?
他们选她！ 她太大 庄士敦！她17了！
They chose her. She's very old,Johnston. She's 17.
那并不大 皇上
That's not so old, Your Majesty.
- 她长得怎样？ - 过时了！
- What does she look like? - Old-fashioned.
我想要个时髦的妻子 庄士敦
I want a modern wife, Johnston...
会说英语 法语
who speaks English and French.
还会跳快步
And who can dance the quickstep.
庄士敦
Johnston
先生
Sir.
我想逃走 庄士敦
I'm going to escape, Johnston.
我搞到个箱子和一张去英国的票
I've got a suitcase and a ticket to England.
我要去牛津大学
I am going to Oxford University.
皇上 若你结婚了 你就会成为自己房子里的主人
Your Majesty, if you get married, you will become the master of your own house.
结婚或许是比较实际的逃避方法
A wedding might be a more practical way to escape.
你为什么从不结婚  庄士敦？
Why did you never get married, Johnston?
噢
oh.
贵妃欢迎皇后
The secondary consort welcomes the empress.
皇后问候贵妃
The empress greets the secondary consort.
你每件事都做得很好
You do everything very well.
谢谢 我练习了很多次
Thank you. I rehearsed many times.
皇上在想什么？
What is His Majesty thinking?
我在想 如果我是真皇帝  我现在就会是中国的统治者
I was thinking if I was a real emperor I would become the ruler of China now.
如果真是这样的话 皇上会做什么呢？
And what would the emperor do if he could really rule?
我会改变所有的事情 甚至我们结婚的方式
I would change everything, even the way we get married.
皇上反对指定的婚姻吗？
Is the emperor against arranged marriages?
耻辱的是不能选择自己的婚姻！
It is humiliating not to choose whom you marry.
就是我 也不能选择
Even I was not allowed to choose.
再过一两年皇上就会比我高了
In another year or two, His Majesty will be taller than me.
皇上在床下有个箱子
Is it true the emperor has a suitcase under his bed...
还想去英国吗？
and is going to oxford?
皇上会带婉容去吗？
Will the emperor take wan Jung with him?
也许他想先看看我的脸再做决定
Perhaps he would like to see my face before he decides.
是的 皇上是想看看皇后的脸
Yes. The emperorwould like to see the face ofthe empress.
应该皇上掀开盖头
It is the emperorwho must remove the kai t'ou.
我也有个象庄士敦先生的导师
I also had a tutor, like Mr.Johnston.
温沙小姐
Miss Windsor.
她是美国人
She's American.
温沙小姐教给我 怎样跳快步舞
Miss Windsor taught me how to do the dance ofthe quickstep.
皇上知道怎样跳快步舞吗？
Does the emperor know how to do the quickstep?
你会教我吗？
Will you teach me?
走开！走开！
Leave us. Leave us.
如果皇上认为
If Your Majesty thinks...
和一个陌生人做云雨之事过时的话
it is old-fashioned to make the rain and the wind with a stranger...
我们可以先做一对现代的夫妇
we can be like a modern couple to begin with.
现代夫妇？
A modern couple?
晚安 晚安
- Good night. - Good night.
你必须和我去牛津大学
You must come to Oxford with me.
我喜欢他！
I like him.
我肯定我会喜欢他！
I am sure I am going to like him.
他会长大！
And he will grow up.
朝下看！
Eyes down!
先报告！
Report your arrival.
- 981号犯人报告 - 大声点！
- Prisoner 981 reporting. - Louder!
981号犯人报告
Prisoner 981 reporting.
开门！
open the door.
关门！
Close the door.
坐下！
Sit down
姓名！
Name.
爱新觉罗・溥仪
Aisin-Gioro Pu Yi.
写下来！
Write it.
听着
Now then.
有两种坦白的方式
There are two types of confession.
我们称为“牙膏”和“水笼头”
We call them toothpaste and water tap.
“牙膏”犯需要常常去挤
The toothpaste prisoner needs to be squeezed every now and then..
否则他会忘记继续坦白
or else he forgets to keep confessing.
“水笼头”犯只需在他开始之前好好地拧一次
The water tap man needs one good, hard twist before he starts...
接着什么都出来了
but then everything comes out.
你是个聪明人
Now, you're an intelligent person
我相信你明白我的话
I'm sure you understand me.
好的
Good.
那我们开始
Then we'll begin.
你知道为什么你在这里吗 981？
Why do you think you're in here, 981?
我被指控叛国、通敌和反革命
I am accused of being a traitor, a collaborator and a counter-revolutionary.
那不是指控！ 你是一个叛国者
It is not an accusation! You are a traitor...
你是一个通敌犯 并且你是一个反革命！
you are a collaborator, and you are a counter-revolutionary!
你把这写下来了？
Did you write this?
你称这是坦白？
And you call it a confession?
这只是个时间表！一个童话！
This is nothing but a list of dates. A child's fairy tale.
- 你们要我坦白什么？ -  你知道你做了什么
- What do you want me to confess? - You know what you did...
别人做了什么
and what others did.
为什么你不志愿提供消息呢？
So why don't you volunteer the information?
我不明白
I do not understand.
我们不告诉犯人坦白什么
We don't tell people what to confess.
我们已经知道你全部的事情
We already know everything about you.
我…
I...
- 继续 - 我要改过自新
- Go on. - I wanted reforms.
你要改什么过？
What did you want to reform?
所有的事
Everything.
剪掉辨子
Cut off my queue.
皇上！不要！
Your Majesty. Please.
- 它很重！- 以前的皇帝被谋杀
- It is heavy. - The emperor before me was murdered..
是因为他们要改革帝国
because he wanted to reform the empire.
是这样吗 庄士敦先生？
Is that not so, Mr.Johnston?
是的 皇上 可能是
Yes, Your Majesty. Probably.
我们看看他们是否杀朕 朕要改革紫禁城
Well, let us see if they will kill me for reforming the Forbidden City.
总管
Lord Chamberlain
朕在任命庄士敦先生的朋友 诗人和学者 陈小苏
I am appointing Mr.Johnston's friend, the poet and scholar Chen Hsiao Hsiu...
来当新的内务总管
to be the new lord chamberlain.
朕要他监督列个详细的库藏清单！
I want him to supervise a detailed inventory of the imperial storerooms...
这样才会知道到底被偷了多少！
so that we can learn exactly how much has been stolen.
紫禁城就象一个没有观众的剧院
The Forbidden City had become a theater without an audience
为什么演员还要留在舞台上呢？
So why did the actors remain on the stage?
仅仅是逐渐偷走布景
It was only to steal the scenery piece by piece.
我能睡这里吗？ 我很害怕
Can I sleep here? I am frightened.
你很勇敢
You're brave.
你不害怕吗？
Are you not frightened?
我很激动 我不想再逃避了
I am excited. I do not want to escape anymore.
我要掌权
I want to rule.
吻我
Kiss me.
我也可以利你呆一起吗？
Can I stay with you as well?
进来 进来
Get in. Get in.
我常和太监玩一个游戏
I used to play a game with the eunuchs.
猜谁是谁
Trying to guess who is who.
我现在看不见你
Now I cannot see you.
嗨
Ah.
- 婉容？
- WanJung?
- 文绣？
- wen Hsiu?
和我们到床单下
Come underneath the sheet with us
皇上！库房着火了 皇上！
Your Majesty. The storerooms are on fire, Your Majesty.
这是个巨大的损失
The fire was a terrible disaster..
并且朕知道是太监们干的 就是要阻止朕查清谁偷了东西
and I knew the eunuchs had started it to stop me from knowing what they had stolen.
紫禁城里面有太监的历史已经800年了
There had been eunuchs in the Forbidden City for 800 years
现在这里仍然有超过1000个太监
There were still more than a thousand of them.
朕决定把他们全部驱逐出去
I decided to expel them all
朕不得不寻求民国军队的帮助
I had to ask for Republican troops to help me.
- 他们能带些什么呢？ - 他们的器官（小JJ）
- What are they carrying? - Their organs.
尽管他们有犯错…
whatever their crimes..
但不能剥夺他们作为一个完整男人埋葬入土的权利
they cannot be deprived of the right to be buried as whole men.
嗯？
Well?
额…
Uh...
- 忘掉我刚才说的吧 - 你在浪费时间
- I have forgot what I was saying. - You are wasting our time!
我们想知道关于日本的事
We want to know about the Japanese.
你和日本人的关系是怎么开始的？
How did your friendship with the Japanese begin?
谁介绍的？！什么时候？！
Who introduced you? When?
我想是在…
I think it was...
是1924年
it was 1 924.
议会再次被解散  总统也跑了
Parliament had been dissolved again. The president had fled.
起初我以为这只是另一个军阀的
At first, I thought it was just another coup d'etat...
另一次政变
by just another warlord.
而这一次确实不一样
Only this time it was different.
这次轮到我了
This time it was my turn.
15比0
Fifteen-love
继续
Play.
30比15
30-15.
腐败的民国政府已经跨台了！
The rotten government of the Republic is in flight.
现在我们要清除东北老鼠的异国臭味…
Now we shall remove the foreign stench of the Manchurian rats...
他们仍藏在紫禁城中
who still hide in the Forbidden City.
“限溥仪及其家人一小时内…
"Mr. Pu Yi and his family have been given one hour...
离开紫禁城
to leave the Forbidden City.
他们将被送到他父亲家
"They will be escorted to the home of his father...
并且作为犯人拘押在那里
"and remain there under guard as state prisoners...
等候通知！
until further notice."
你们看什么？
What are you all looking at?
站那里发什么呆？
What are you standing there for?
你们总得离开紫禁城
You always wanted to leave the Forbidden City.
你们只有一小时时间收拾 所以快去！
Now you've got an hour to pack. So go!
快啊！
Go!
我总以为我恨这里
I always thought I hated it here.
现在我害怕离开
Now I'm afraid to leave
- 你认为他们会杀我吗？ - 按他们说的做 皇上
- Do you think they will kill me? - You must do as they say, Your Majesty...
我将去英国大使馆
while I try to reach the British Embassy
他们会给你庇护权
They will give you asylum there
我肯定他们会的
I'm sure they will.
张 把我的车开到南门！ 我要送皇上
Chang, take my car to the south gate. I want you to drive His Majesty.
皇上！
Your Majesty!
- 请 皇上！ - 什么？
- Please, Your Majesty. - What?
但你没有去英国使馆 是不是？
But you didn't go to the British Embassy, did you?
你反而去了日本使馆
You ended up at the Japanese Embassy.
日本人是唯一准备帮助我的人
The Japanese were the only people prepared to help me.
他们白帮你？
Help you for nothing?
日本有个皇帝 我们年龄差不多
Japan has an emperor. We are almost the same age.
我想是出于善意
I thought it was kindness.
同时我意识到很多中国人 认为我是异族人
At the same time I realized that, for many Chinese, I was an alien...
只是因为我是满洲人
simply because I am Manchurian.
甚至有个反满同盟要暗杀我！
There was even an anti-Manchurian league who wanted to assassinate me.
所以 我想住在天津
So I went to live in Tientsin.
那是有个大港口的好地方
It was a nice, provincial town with a big port.
那些日子  我们做了重大的决定
In those days they had a large international settlement
日本人认为我在那里会安全些
The Japanese thought it would be safer for me there
在天津日本人替你付钱吗？
were the Japanese paying for you in Tientsin?
噢 不是
oh, no.
我只好租一栋公馆 张公馆
I had to rent a villa - the Villa Chang.
非常昂贵
And it was very expensive.
保镖也是
So were the bodyguards.
我在天津花了很多钱
I spent a lot of money in Tientsin
你那时还想恢复大清帝国吗？
Did you still believe in a restoration of the imperial system?
其他人想 后来被抓并流放了
others did. The little court in exile
我记不清他们让我花费了多少 翡翠珠宝
I cannot remember how much jade and jewelry they made me spend...
来讨好一些军阀利一些俄国将军
to buy the friendship of some warlord or some White Russian general.
你的钱还花在哪儿了？
What else did you spend your money on?
我是不厌其烦地买钢琴  手表 收音机…
I was never tired of buying pianos, watches, radios.
只要是外国造的都买！
As long as they were foreign
当然
of course.
西方的任何东西都好
Anything western was good.
特别是WrigLey口香糖  Bayer阿斯匹林和汽车
Especially Wrigley's Chewing Gum, Bayer Aspirin, and cars.
你在天津时…
While you were in Tientsin...
中国大部分土地由蒋介石统治
most of China came under the control of General Chiang Kai-shek...
号称民族主义的
the so-called nationalists...
国民党
the Kuomintang.
- 你利他们是什么关系？- 没有
- What were your relations with them? - None.
我觉得留在天津毫无意义
I felt useless in Tientsin.
我都21岁了
I was 21 .
我梦想去西方
I dreamt of going to the west.
我变成了花花公子
I became a playboy.
我忧郁
# Am I blue #
我沮丧
我眼中的泪水会
# Ain't these tears in my eyes #
告诉你
# Telling you #
我忧郁
# Am I blue #
你也会这样
# You'd be too #
如果你和女友
# If each plan with your girl #
分手了
# Done fell through #
曾经
# Was a time #
我是她的唯一
# I was her only one #
但是现在
# But now #
我又悲伤又孤独
# I'm the sad and lonely one #
现在她走了 我们也结束了
# Now she's gone and we're through #
上帝啊 我忧郁
# Lord, I'm blue
太棒了！
Very good!
很好！
well done!
那船很棒 如果您坐头等舱
That's a great ship if you're going first class.
我哪里也不去
I am not going anywhere.
想跳舞吗？
Would you like to dance?
你很勇敢  这里没人敢和我跳舞
You are a brave man. Nobody here would have danced with me.
为什么？
Why is that?
因为我是中国人
Because I'm Chinese.
我是美国人
Well, I'm American.
你说加利福尼亚 我说法国里维埃拉
You say California. I say French Riviera.
说弗朗西斯科（旧金山）！
San Francisco!
蒙特卡洛！
Monte Carlo!
这次我们真的走吗？
Are we really going this time?
那一对是谁？
Who's that couple?
是亨利和伊丽莎白
Oh. Henry and Elizabeth.
中国的皇帝？
The emperor of China?
以前的皇帝和他的妻子
The ex-emperor and his wife.
- 她很漂亮 - 是的 非常
- She's beautiful. - Yes, very.
那你是谁？
And who are you?
- 我是殿下的另一个妻子 -他的另一个妻子？
- I am His Highness's other wife. - His otherwife?
二号妻子
Number two wife.
是吗 有些人真是幸运
Well, some people have all the luck.
女士们先生们！
Ladies and gentlemen!
蒋介石将军
General Chiang Kai-shek...
已经占领了上海
has taken Shanghai.
国民党已与共产党决裂
The Kuomintang have broken with the Reds...
并6次击败了他们！
and have knocked them for six!
-共产党完了！
- The Reds are finished!
对此次接见的每一个人表示歉意
Sorry about the reception, everyone. We'll get it fixed in a minute.
现在最好返回日本领事馆 皇上
It would be wiser to return to the Japanese Legation now, Your Majesty.
- 您的车准备好了 - 谢谢你 甘糟先生
- Your car is waiting. -Thank you, Mr. Amakasu.
出发吧
Here we go.
上海的总罢工已经失败了
The general strike in Shanghai has collapsed
国际租借很安全的
The international settlement is safe
国民党军队…
Troops of the Kuomintang..
完全控制了这个城市
are now in full control ofthe city...
正用有力的措施恢复平民区的秩序
and firm steps are being taken to restore order in the native areas
文绣 要口香糖吗？
Wen Hsiu, you want some gum?
我要离婚
I want a divorce.
我再也不想当你的情妇了
I do not want to be your mistress any longer.
我认为你是我的贵妃
I thought you were my secondary consort.
在紫禁城 你是皇帝我是贵妃
In the Forbidden City, you were the emperor and I was your secondary consort.
但现在你是亨利溥仪
But now you are Henry Pu Yi.
婉容是你的妻子 伊丽莎白
Wan Yung is your wife, Elizabeth.
那我算什么？
And who am I?
我什么都不是
I'm nobody.
我不知道你这么不高兴
I did not know you were so unhappy.
在西方你只能娶一个妻子
You can only have one wife in the West.
我要离婚
I want a divorce.
没人能和我离婚！
No one can divorce me.
我要离婚！
I want a divorce!
夫人！
Your Ladyship!
谢谢
Thank you.
我不需要！
I do not need it!
I do not need it.
文绣
Wen Hsiu.
伊丽莎白！我可以进来吗？
Elizabeth, can I come in?
不记得我了？我穿得象个飞行员
Don't you remember me?
我穿得象个飞行员 但我还不能飞！还不能
I'm dressed like a pilot, but I still can't fly. Not yet.
东方明珠！ 我们一起上舞蹈课！
Eastern Jewel! We had dancing classes together.
是的 恰在你结婚前
Yes, just before your marriage.
傻女孩 为什么人想要结婚呢？
You silly girl. Why do people want to get married?
文绣走了
Wen Hsiu has gone.
她再也不会回来了
She will never come back.
那很糟糕吗？
Is that so bad?
她是我唯一的朋友
She was my only friend.
是的  但至少你可以独享你的丈夫了！
Well, at least now you've got your husband all to yourself.
你有了我！
And you've got me!
我会做你的朋友
I'll be your friend.
- 你吸鸦片？ - 可恶
- You smoke opium? - Be wicked.
这是上海最好的东西
It's the best in Shanghai.
什么你要去欧洲？
Why are you going to Europe?
应该去日本！ 哪儿比任何地方都有趣！
The place to go is Japan. It's more fun than anywhere.
时髦的地方
It's modern
你怎么知道我们要去欧洲？ 这是个秘密
How do you know we are going to Europe? It is a secret.
我知道所有的事！
Oh, I know everything.
我知道蒋介石有假牙
I know Chiang Kai-shek has got false teeth.
我甚至知道他的绰号 “给我换现金！”
I even know his nickname..."Cash My Check!"
我是间谍…
I'm a spy...
我不怕别人知道
and I don't care who knows it.
- 间谍？ - 我为日本特别行动部工作
- A spy? - I work for the Japanese Special Service Bureau.
我是来保护你的
And I've come to protect you.
日本人…
The Japanese...
他们越来越接近他
They are getting closer to him every day.
他正想送他弟弟去东京的军事学院
He is sending his brother to the military academy in Tokyo.
他们一直利他谈论满洲的事
They talk to him about Manchuria all the time.
甘糟先生不再和我打招呼
And Mr. Amakasu never says hello to me.
我不信任日本人
I do not trust the Japanese.
当然 我很想当皇帝的第二夫人！
Of course, I'd love to be the emperor's new secondary consort.
- 东方明珠 - 如果那位子能够得到
- Eastern Jewel. - If the post is available.
那位子是空着 亲爱的表妹
The post is vacant, my dear cousin.
但你不适合那位子
But you do not fit the part.
文绣把狗拉下了 你想要吗？
Wen Hsiu left the dog behind. Do you want it?
是我的错
It is my fault.
都是我的错
It is all my fault.
我来看看您 皇上
I came to see you, Your Majesty...
给您带来了坏消息
to give you bad news.
一些可怕的事发生了
Something terrible has happened
我们满洲先皇的陵墓
The imperial tombs of our Manchurian ancestors...
被盗掘了
have been attacked and robbed...
是国民党军队干的
by troops of the Kuomintang
是中国士兵
Chinese soldiers
一个蒋介石手下的军阀
A warlord working for Chiang Kai-shek
慈禧太后的遗体
The body of the Empress Dowager...
被劈成了碎片
was hacked to pieces.
她的珍珠项链成了蒋介石的一个结婚礼物
Her pearl necklace has become a wedding present from Chiang Kai-shek...
给他新妻子的
to his new wife.
告诉我 981号 你想不想成为一个中国人？
Tell me, 981 , do you consider yourself to be Chinese?
当然想
of course.
- 这是什么？ - 日本
- What is this? -Japan.
- 你把中国的这个部分叫什么？ - 东北
- And what do you call this part ofChina? - The northeast.
- 你小时候把它叫什么？- 满洲
- And what did you call it as a child? - Manchuria.
日本在1931年9月18日入侵了满洲
Japan invaded Manchuria on September 18, 1931 ...
并开始建立一个叫满洲国的傀儡国家
and began to set up a puppet state called Manchukuo.
之后不久 一个日本代表团在天津对你进行了一次秘密拜访
Shortly afterwards, a Japanese delegation paid you a secret visit in Tientsin...
请求你的合作
to request your collaboration.
你拒绝了吗？
Would you say you refused?
- 大声说！ - 我已经告诉了你们
- Speak up! - I already told you.
- 我对你们说了一百遍了 - 再说一遍！跟我们说200遍！
- I have told you a hundred times. - Tell us again. Tell us 200 times.
我拒绝合作
I refused to collaborate.
你说你拒绝了
You say you refused.
但一个月后 在1931年11月10日 你到了满洲
But a month later, on November 10, 1931 , there you are arriving in Manchuria.
或许我应该称它为满洲国？
or should I call it Manchukuo?
根据你的这份所谓的供词
Now, according to this so-called confession of yours...
你并不是自愿走的
you didn't go of your own free will.
你坚持说 你是被日本人绑架去的！
You insist that you were kidnapped by theJapanese!
- 是的 - 是被强迫带到满洲的
- Yes. - And taken to Manchuria by force
- 是的！ - 坐下
- Yes! - Sit down.
你记不记得一个叫雷金纳德.弗莱明.庄士敦的人？
Do you remember a man called Reginald Fleming Johnston?
他是你的私人教师
He was your tutor.
是的
Yes.
还是好朋友 我想
And a good friend, I believe.
在中国待了28年后
After 28 years in China...
庄士敦回到了英格兰
Mr.Johnston returned to England.
他成了伦敦大学的一个东方文化的教授
He became a professor of Oriental Studies at London University...
他写了一本书
and he wrote a book
书名是《紫禁城的黄昏》
It is called Twilight in the Forbidden City...
它是献给你的
and it is dedicated to you.
再见！
Bye now!
- 再见！ - 再见了！
- Bye! - Good-bye!
- 别忘了写信 - 再见噢！
- Don't forget to write! - Bye, Mom!
我会想念你的 庄士顿
I am going to miss you, Johnston.
我也会想念你 皇上
I shall miss you, Your Majesty.
你认为一个人可以再次成为皇帝么？
Do you think a man can become emperor again?
是的
Yes.
谢谢您 皇上
Thank you, Your Majesty.
全部上船！全部上船！全部上船！
All aboard! All aboard! All aboard!
我们怎能说“再见”？
How can we say good-bye?
就象我们说“您好”
As we said hello.
再见 庄士敦先生
Farewell, Mr.Johnston.
再见 皇上！
Farewell, Your Majesty.
全部上船！全部上船！
All aboard! All aboard!
谢谢你
Thank you.
Thank you
全部上船！全部上船！
- All aboard! - All aboard!
现在全部上船！
All aboard now!
全部上船！
All aboard!
再见 庄士顿先生！
Good-bye, Mr.Johnston!
我们永远不会忘记你 庄士敦先生
We'll never forget you, Mr.Johnston!
再见！庄士敦先生 再见！再见！
Good-bye! Mr.Johnston, good-bye!
- 再见！ - 全部上船！
- Good-bye! - All aboard!
在第449页…
On page 449...
庄士敦先生写到
Mr.Johnston writes:
声称皇帝是被日本人绑架一事
"The endeavor to make out that the emperor had been kidnapped by the Japanese...
完全是不真实的
"is wholly untrue.
他离开天津去满洲…
"He left Tientsin and went to Manchuria...
是他完全自愿的
of his own free will."
- 庄士敦在说谎！- 你说什么？
-Johnston was a liar. - what did you say?
庄士敦先生在我被带去满洲前就已离开了
Mr.Johnston had left before I was taken to Manchuria.
他不知道都发生了什么事情
He could not have known what happened.
坐下
Sit down.
根据这份供词 你在11月9日的早晨把这个人的行李打点好的
According to this account, you prepared the man's things on the morning of November 9.
对一个被绑架的人来说
Isn't it unusual for a man who is kidnapped...
在他被绑架的前一天让仆人准备好行李 这正常吗？
to have his luggage packed by his valet the day before he is kidnapped?
这是你写的 是不是？ 是谁让你去准备这个人的行李的？
This is what you have written, isn't it? Who told you to pack this man's luggage?
这两个故事不相符 不是吗？
These two stories don't fit, do they?
时间太久了
It was a long time ago.
大概我弄错了
Perhaps I made a mistake.
你在说谎！你们都在说谎！
You are lying! You are both lying!
冷静点！
Control yourself!
你仍然可以改变你的看法
You can still change your mind.
我是满洲人民的世袭统治者
I am the hereditary ruler of the Manchurian people.
没有我就没有满洲国
There can be no Manchukuo without me.
你没看出来？日本人在利用你
Do you not see? The Japanese are using you.
我必须试着利用他们
I must try to use them.
日本对满洲的侵略将被国际联盟所谴责
The Japanese invasion of Manchuria will be condemned by the League of Nations...
包括地球上所有的文明国家
and by every civilized country on Earth.
民国违背了它对我许下的每一个诺言！
The Chinese Republic has broken every promise it ever made to me.
中国军队侮辱了我先祖的陵墓！
Chinese troops desecrated the tombs of my ancestors.
并且中国军队没有在日本进攻时保卫满洲！
And Chinese troops did not defend Manchuria from the Japanese.
但满洲仍是中国！
But Manchuria is still China!
- 中国已经抛弃了我 - 请不要走
- China has turned its back on me. - Please, do not go.
满洲是最富饶的亚洲边疆！
Manchuria is the richest frontier in Asia.
煤 油 铁路！
Coal, oil, railways!
每年都有上百万的中国移民去那里！
Millions of Chinese immigrants are going there every year.
我将建立我的国家
I'm going to build my country.
庄士敦错了 但他不是个说谎者
Johnston was wrong, but he wasn't a liar.
不存在绑架！
There was no kidnapping.
去满洲是你自己的选择 是因为你想再次成为皇帝！
You went to Manchuria by your own choice because you wanted to be emperor again!
这些东西或许能帮助你回忆真相
These might help you to remember the truth.
对天
To heaven.
对地
To earth.
对月
To the moon
对日
To the sun.
你又是皇后了
You're an empress again.
我想做的是飞行员！
What I'm going to be is a pilot.
我将在横滨附近的一个秘密基地训练学习精确轰炸
I'm going to train at a secret base near Yokohama to learn precision bombing.
我想轰炸上海
I want to bomb Shanghai.
轰炸上海？
Bomb Shanghai?
我恨中国！
I hate China.
我恨你
I hate you.
日本军最高统帅部！ 印象深刻！
The Japanese army high command. Very impressive!
日本军队！
The Japanese army!
快！
Quickly!
代表日本天皇
On behalf of the emperor of Japan...
关东军司令官表达他最热烈的祝贺
the commander of the Kwangtung Army extends his warmest congratulations...
在皇帝的加冕仪式上
on the occasion of His Majesty's coronation
呵 是的
Ah, yes.
满洲国将成为一个伟大的国家
Manchukuo will grow into a great nation
日本将一直站在皇帝一边
Japan will always be at her side to help her.
我给你介绍一下？
Uh, may I introduce you?
- 我妻子 广岛公主
- My wife, the Princess Hiro Saga.
总理大臣郑孝胥
Prime Minister Hsiao Hsiu
尊敬的国防大臣张景惠
The Honorable Chang Chinghui Minister of Defense.
教廷特使 科隆阁下
The Papal Nuncio, Monsignor Colonna.
朕和皇后非常高兴地接受…
The empress and I accept with great pleasure...
对不起 将军
Excuse me, General.
还有我们的甘粕先生
Ah, and our Mr. Amakasu...
他是满洲电影会的新主席
is the new chief of the Manchurian Motion Picture Studios.
为什么你不好好享受呢？
Why do you have to spoil this day?
为什么？
Why?
甘粕先生是满洲国最有权势的人
Mr. Amakasu is the most powerful man in Manchukuo.
你在说什么？
What are you talking about?
你不相信我能再当皇帝 但我是了
You did not believe I could be emperor again, but I am.
你糊涂
You are blind.
你知道当皇后意味着什么吗？ 你是皇后！
Do you know what it means to be an empress? You are an empress.
为什么你不再和我做爱？
Why do you not make love to me anymore?
因为你已经成了鸦片鬼
Because you have become an opium addict.
鸦片杀了我母亲  鸦片毁了中国
Opium killed my mother. Opium destroyed China.
你可在满洲国任何地方买到鸦片！
You can buy opium anywhere in Manchukuo.
- 住口！ - 在任一个商店
- Shut up. - In any shop.
住口！
Shut up!
你弟弟要生小孩了
Your brother is going to have a child.
我们必须有个孩子
we must have a child
我们必须有个继承人
You must have an heir.
裕仁天皇正式邀请我们访问日本
Emperor Hirohito has officially invited us to Japan.
我将单独去
I'm going alone.
你呆在这里
You are staying here
我再也不会去日本
I will never go to Japan.
那回你的房间去
Then go to your room.
皇上万岁！
Ten thousand years to His Majesty the Emperor!
- 万岁！ - 万岁！
- Ten thousand years! - Ten thousand years!
皇上万岁！
Ten thousand years to His Majesty, the Emperor!
万岁！
Ten thousand years!
万岁！ 万岁！
Ten thousand years! Ten thousand years!
告诉你 我恨你
I told you I hate you.
只是因为我满足你一切吗
Only because I give you what you need.
我们现在是一对了
Now we're engaged.
- 你忘了我的牙粉 - 哦
- You forgot my tooth powder. - oh.
是的 先生
Yes, sir.
换掉他
Move him.
981号！收拾你的东西！
981 , collect your things
上楼！
Upstairs!
站住！
Stop.
你的鞋带开了 系好！
Your laces are undone. Do them up.
星期四 你准备午餐 星期五 打扫洗漱间
Thursday you serve lunch. Friday you clean the toilet.
星期天 打扫走廊
Saturday you sweep the floor.
我从未和家人分开过
I have never been separated from my family.
你最好能习惯！
You'd better get used to it.
你不记得我了 是不是？
You do not remember me, do you?
我是满洲国的贸易部长
I was the minister of trade in Manchukuo.
你们都在满洲国
You were all in Manchukuo.
现在 我是狱头
Now I am the cell leader.
在这里守规矩很重要 学习时不要讲话
It is important to follow the rules here. No talking during study sessions.
你的枪呢 队长？
Where is your gun, Captain?
他们的剑呢？
Where are their swords?
我们的武器被收了 皇上
Our weapons have been removed, Your Majesty...
根据吉冈町上校的命令
on the orders of Colonel Yoshioka.
吉冈町上校？
Colonel Yoshioka?
- 吉冈町上校 - 这里发生了什么？
- Colonel Yoshioka. - What has happened here?
为什么我的卫兵被缴械？
Why has my guard been disarmed?
非常不幸 皇上
Yes, it is very unfortunate, Your Majesty.
自从你去了东京 这里发生了许多变化
There have been many changes while you were in Tokyo.
皇上 我向您介绍Masaomi KobayaKawa
Your Majesty, may I present Masaomi Kobayakawa...
日本驻满洲国新大使
the new Japanese ambassador to Manchukuo.
为什么总理大臣郑孝胥不来接我？
Why is Prime Minister Hsiao Hsiu not here to receive me?
总理大臣辞职了 皇上
The prime minister has resigned, Your Majesty.
他的儿子被暗杀了
His son has been assassinated.
暗杀了？
Assassinated?
共匪干的 皇上
By Communist bandits, Your Majesty.
我必须马上见他
I must see him at once.
他拒绝见任何人 皇上
He refuses to see anyone, Your Majesty.
他已经出家了
He has gone to a monastery...
很远的地方
far away.
你是谁？
Who are you?
张景惠 皇上
Chang Chinghui, Your Majesty...
国防大臣
Minister of Defense.
是的
Yes.
当然了
of course.
议会4点开 皇上
The council meeting will be at 4:00, Your Majesty...
国宴之前
before the state dinner.
皇上必须签署这些文件
"The emperor has been asked to sign the following.
在仔细考虑之后
"After careful consideration...
我们决定提名张景惠…
"we have decided to nominate the Honorable Chang Chinghui...
当满洲国的新总理大臣
as the new prime minister of Manchukuo."
不
No.
在我们从日本回来后的今天...
Today, on our return from Japan...
我们想讲一些更重要的事情…
we wish to speak ofsomething more important...
我们和日本友好关系的未来
the future of our friendship with Japan.
这基于相互尊重之上
This is based on mutual respect.
尊重意味着平等和独立
And respect means equality and independence.
当两个皇帝站在一起 向两国国旗致敬时
When the two emperors stood together and saluted the two national flags...
他们认识到满洲国的重要性(成年了)
they recognized that Manchukuo had come of age.
满洲国不是殖民地  满洲国就是满洲
Manchukuo is not a colony. Manchukuo is Manchuria.
两国之间的关系…
The relationship between our two countries...
就象两个皇帝之间的关系
is like the relationship between its two emperors.
它基于仁慈的信任
It is rooted in fraternal trust..
来…
in...
来实现保持我们古老传统的愿望
in the desire to preserve our ancient traditions...
并且在相互尊重下保持我们的民族统一
and in a mutual respect for our national identities!
我们已经迎来了一些大使…
Already we have welcomed the ambassadors...
萨尔瓦多 哥斯达黎加 梵蒂冈
of El Salvador, Costa Rica the Vatican.
我相信其他国家不久也会来的
Soon, I'm...I'm sure the other countries will follow.
我怀孕了
I'm going to have a child.
父亲是满洲人
The father is Manchurian.
吉冈和甘粕先生
Colonel and Mr. Amakasu!
我是为你做的！
I did it for you.
皇上忘了签署新总理大臣任命！
His Majesty forgot to sign the appointment of the new prime minister...
张景惠先生
Mr. Chang Chinghui.
我没忘
I did not forget.
当一个英国人抢劫某人时 皇上
When an Englishman robs someone, Your Majesty...
他就成了一个绅士
he becomes a gentleman.
如果他抢劫多人 他就成了骑士
If he robs a lot, he becomes a knight.
你以为英国人把他们的帝国当成一个慈善团体？
Do you imagine the British run their empire as a charity?
如果印度不得不为他的被占领付钱
If India has paid for the cost of its own occupation...
那满洲国也必须付
so must Manchukuo!
我们希望满洲国有个继承人
We hope Manchukuo will have an heir.
皇后正怀孕
The empress is expecting a child.
是的 皇上 我们明白这情况
Yes, Your Majesty. we are aware of the situation
这是父亲的名字
This is the name of the father.
他叫Chang！
His name is Chang
他是你的司机
He is your driver.
必要的证据都记录下来了
All the necessary facts have been recorded
他要受到惩罚
The man will be punished.
皇帝不允许他的尊严被玷污
The emperor cannot allow his honor to be stained.
日本人是地球上唯一神圣的民族
The Japanese are the only divine race on earth.
我们将占领中国  香港 印度尼西亚
We will take China, Hong Kong, Indochina...
暹罗 马来西亚
Siam, Malaya...
新加坡和印度！
Singapore and India!
亚洲属于我们！
Asia belongs to us!
你同屋的人对你有抱怨
There have been complaints from your cell mates.
你必须学会夜里小便时不把别人搞醒！
You must learn how to urinate at night without waking them all up.
方法是洒尿时顺着桶边…
The way to do it is to urinate against the side of the bucket...
而不是尿到中间
not into the middle.
是 同志
Yes, comrade
你还以为我是你的仆人  是不是？
You still think I am your servant, don't you?
你都是在假装
You are all pretending.
你假装成你已经改正了
You are just pretending you have changed.
住口！党会把我们教育成新人的！
Shut up! The party teaches us to be new men while working for a new China!
你在甘粕的私人办公室工作
You worked in Amakasu's private office.
你们还是原来的老样子！ 人不会改变
You are still the same people. People do not change.
卫兵！卫兵！
Guard! Guard!
卫兵！
Guard!
- 是我造成的 - 卫兵！
- I let it happen. - Guard!
- 卫兵！ - 是我造成的
- Guard! - I let it happen.
噢！
Ohh!
第二个法令 皇上
The second edict, Your Majesty.
日语将做满洲国学校的官方语言
Japanese will be the official language in Manchukuo schools.
皇上！
Your Majesty!
小孩生下来就死了 皇上
The baby was born dead, Your Majesty.
皇后怎样？
How is the empress?
如果她去诊所或暖和点的地方就好了
It will be better if she goes to a clinic, Somewhere warm.
她已经离开了 皇上
She's already left, Your Majesty.
开门
Open the door.
日本将满洲国牢牢地控制住后…
With Manchukuo now firmly in their grasp...
不久就控制了中国北部的大部分地区
the Japanese soon controlled most of North China.
1937年 他们做好了南攻的准备
By 1937 they were ready to strike south...
对准了这个国家的心脏
at the heart of the country.
进攻上海是历史上第一次对平民的轰炸
The attack on Shanghai was one of the first civilian bombing raids in history.
它使千万人无家可归  千万人死去
It left thousands homeless, thousands dead.
三个月以后 日本军队包围了南京的临时政府
Three months later, Japanese armies were besieging the provisional capital at Nanking...
城市沦陷后 暴行开始了
and when the city fell the atrocities began.
为了恐吓中国的幸存者…
Trying to terrorize the rest of China into surrender...
日本最高统帅部命令的这场屠杀
the Japanese high command ordered a massacre.
2千多万平民被有系统地杀害
More than 200,000 civilians were systematically executed.
整个世界都看呆了
The world watched in horror..
但没人给予帮助
but no help was given.
1941年12月7日
On December 7, 1941...
日本袭击了 驻珍珠港的美国舰队
Japan attacked the American fleet at Pearl Harbor.
没有事先警告
There was no warning.
满洲国 日本在中国东北的基地…
Manchukuo, the Japanese bastion in North China...
仍被傀儡皇帝溥仪统治
was still ruled by the puppet emperor Pu Yi.
但是在成功的背后…
But behind the facade oftriumph...
是一个国家的被奴役…
was a country enslaved...
在这个国家 日本进行了细菌战…
a country where Japanese experiments in biological warfare...
进行了活体实验…
were carried out on live human beings...
在这个国家 鸦片的种植成了资助战争最廉价的方式
a country where opium production became the easiest way to finance the war.
数百万人被故意地诱导成吸毒者
Millions of people were deliberately turned into drug addicts.
广岛原子弹爆炸后的第9天…
Nine days after the bomb at Hiroshima...
即1945年8月15日…
on August 15, 1945...
裕仁天皇宣布日本投降
Emperor Hirohito announced the surrender ofJapan.
他的声音第一次出现在收音机中
It was the first time his voice had ever been heard on radio.
你必须去东京 皇上
You must get to Tokyo, Your Majesty
你必须向美国投降 而不是向俄国人
You must surrender to the Americans, not the Russians.
共产党会杀了所有的人
The Communists will kill everyone.
皇后回来了
The empress has returned.
皇上 请
Majesty, please.
皇上！
Your Majesty!
快！飞机上没地方了 皇上！
Hurry! There is no room on the plane, Your Majesty!
女人没有危险！ 我们要快！
The women are not in danger! we must hurry!
皇上！皇上现在要走！
Your Majesty! Your Majesty is leaving now!
现在！
Now!
俄国人！
The Russians!
你以为我们在这里是为了教人们撒谎的新办法
Perhaps you think we are here to teach men to lie in a new way
为什么所有对你的指控 你都承认？
Why did you sign every accusation made against you?
我不想看到你象要自杀的样子…
I didn't stop you from killing yourself to see you like this...
一个为取媚于敌人什么都签署的人  又取媚于我！
someone who signs anything to please his enemies, to please me!
你知道满洲国的很多事情…
You knew about a lot of things in Manchukuo...
甚至秘密协议…
even the secret agreement...
但是你并不能知道…
but you couldn't possibly have known...
日本人在哈尔滨进行的细菌战实验！
about theJapanese biological warfare experiments in Harbin.
你能吗？
Could you?
为什么你承认这些呢？
So why did you sign these papers?
我对所有的事负责
I was responsible for everything.
你对你所做的事负责！
You are responsible for what you do!
在你一生中 你以为你比任何人优越
All your life you thought you were better than everyone else.
现在你认为你比任何人倒霉！
Now you think you are the worst of all!
为什么不让我独处一会？
Why can you not leave me alone?
你救我是为了让我在你的游戏中当木偶
You saved my life to make me a puppet in your own play.
你救我是因为我对你有用
You saved me because I am useful to you.
那么可怕…
Is that so terrible...
为了有用？
to be useful?
爱新觉罗・溥仪
Aisin-Gioro Pu Yi.
最高人民法院令…
By order of the Supreme People's Court...
战犯爱新觉罗溥仪…
the war criminal Aisin-Gioro Pu Yi...
男 53岁…
male, 53 years old...
满洲人…
of the Manchu nationality...
来自北京…
and from Peking...
现已拘押了10年！
has now served 10 years' detention.
在其关押期间经过劳动思想改造…
As a result of remolding through labor...
和意识形态方面的教育…
and ideological education during his captivity...
用行动证明了他已改过自新！
he has shown that he has genuinely reformed.
根据特赦令中的条款…
In accordance with clause one of the Special Pardon order...
他被特赦
he is therefore to be released
你明白？
You see?
我会在监狱待得比你长
I will end up living in prison longer than you.
红卫兵
The Red Guards.
他们那么年轻
They are so young.
那很危险
It is dangerous.
看
Look.
那儿 蒲节 看！
Over there. Pu Chieh, look!
是我们的监狱长！
It is the governor of our prison!
- 不会的！ - 是的！
- It cannot be. - It is!
我肯定是的！
I'm sure it is!
小心！
Be careful.
回来！
Come back!
同志这肯定是个误会！
Comrade, this must be a mistake.
我认识这个人！他是个好人
I know this man. He is a good man.
- 你是谁？ - 我是个花匠
- Who are you? - I am a gardener.
加入我们 同志 否则走开！
Join us, comrade, or fuck off!
但他做了什么？
But what has he done?
- 他被指控 - 指控什么？
- He has been accused. - Accused of what?
- 帝国主义者！- 反革命分子！
- Emperor's lackey! - Revisionist element!
叛国者！
Rotten rightist!
- 交待你的罪行！ - 我没什么要交待的
- Confess your crime. - I have nothing to confess.
向毛主席磕头
Kowtow to Chairman Mao.
- 交待你的罪行！ - 我没什么要交待的
- Confess your crimes. - I have nothing to confess.
磕头！
Kowtow!
- 交待你的罪行！ - 等等！
- Confess your crimes! - Wait!
他是个老师！ 他是个好老师！
He's a teacher! He is a good teacher!
- 你们不能这样对他！ - 滚！滚！
- You...You cannot do this to him! - Move! Move!
你们错了！ 他是个好老师！
You are wrong! He is a good teacher!
站住！
Stop!
你不许到那里！
You are not allowed in there!
- 你是谁？ - 我住这里
- Who are you? - I live here.
我是花匠的儿子！
I am the son of the guardian.
是吗 我原来也住这里
Ah, well, I used to live here too.
- 我原来就坐那里 - 你是谁？
- That is where I sat. - who are you?
我原是中国的皇帝
I was the emperor of China.
证明呢！
Prove it!
这里是太和殿…
This is the Hall of Supreme Harmony...
皇帝加冕的地方
where the emperors were crowned.
在这里加冕的最后一个皇帝是爱新觉罗・溥仪
The last emperor to be crowned here was Aisin-Gioro Pu Yi.
他那时3岁
He was three years old.